בוקר טוב, Boker tov, אלול טוב, Elul tov, everybody reminded to do
תשובה. teshuvah. Okay, pickup on today's דף daf is, well, where we're
up to is פ"ו עמוד ב'. peh-vav amud bet. So we'll say
that today's דף daf is, we'll finish up פ"ו peh-vav and do
פ"ז. peh-zayin. We pick up with the משנה mishna on פ"ו עמוד
ב' peh-vav amud bet and we're still dealing with the הפרה hafara
of the husband. So let's take a look. A lot of this
has been focusing on what constitutes עינוי נפש inui nefesh or דברים
שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino lveinah, and now we get a little bit
more into the act of הפרה hafara itself. נדרה אשתו וסבר שנדרה
בתו: Nadar ishto vsavar shenadar bito: a man's wife took a vow
but he thought it was his daughter, or, right, two people that
he can annul all their vows. Or נדרה בתו וסבר שנדרה אשתו,
nadra bito vsavar shenadra ishto, or his daughter and he thought it
was his wife. נדרה בנזיר וסבר שנדרה בקרבן: Nadra benazir vsavar shenadra
bekorban: a woman made a vow that she'd be a נזיר, nazir,
but he thought that she made some vow using the sort of
קרבן korban terminology. Now it's interesting, right, presumably it's not just a
question of terminology. Let's say it was נדרה בקונם וסבר שנדרה בקרבן
nadra bekonam vsavar shenadra bekorban or something like that, you know, or
she made a, or she, or well, could be, that's a, right,
maybe that's not even the best different example. But let's say she
just made a נדר סתם neder stam and he thought he used
the word קרבן. korban. I mean, that would be like a difference
that would be without a distinction as it were or that would
not be so material, but presumably here it's a very different type
of a נדר neder that he thought she made, which actually could
be like, the whole, and in a way this is more of
a technical point than any of the rest, because that could be
his basis for annulling it might have been on a faulty basis.
Of course maybe you could suggest the same about wife and daughter,
what he wants to annul for his wife is not what he
wants to annul for his daughter. So there could be here some
substantive reasons why he would not have wanted to annul one way
or the other, but it sounds like the משנה mishna is not
concerned with that. That basically the point is you have to know
whom you're annulling for and what it is you're annulling. נדרה בקרבן,
Nadra bekorban, so נדרה בנזיר וסבר שנדרה בקרבן, nadra benazir vsavar shenadra
bekorban, נדרה בקרבן וסבר שנדרה בנזיר, nadra bekorban vsavar shenadra benazir, or
she made a נדר neder with the קרבן korban language and he
thought she made a נזיר nazir נדר. neder. נדרה
מתאנים וסבר שנדרה מן ענבים: Nadra mite'einim vsavar shenadra min anavim: she
made a vow not to eat figs and he thought she made
a vow not to eat grapes. Or נדרה מן ענבים וסבר שנדרה
מן התאנים, nadra min anavim vsavar shenadra min hate'einim, or the reverse.
In all these cases he either did not know who made the
vow, what object it was made on, or what exactly the type
of the vow was. הרי זה יחזור ויפר. Harei ze yachzor veyafer.
So in all those cases he either, he must be, let's read
it that he tried to be מיפר mefer thinking those things, in
all those cases he must go back and be מיפר mefer if
he wants it to be הופר. hufar. Another way to read this
that the ר"ן Ran says, or both might be true is, he
was מקיים mekayem it thinking any of these things. That קיום kiyum
is not a problem because it's a קיום kiyum also based on
error and he is still enabled to go back and to be
מיפר. mefer. So whether קיום kiyum or whether הפרה, hafara, the גמרא
gemara is going to say this, not clear in the משנה, mishna,
you have to know for whom, what object and what type of
a נדר. neder.
Now, did he say until the end of the day from
when he realized he was mistaken? No, you still have ביום שמעו,
beyom sham'o, you just made, well, actually what happens if in there
are certain errors we're going to get to in a coming משנה,
mishna, but that's when you sort of didn't realize that it was
a type of a נדר neder you could have annulled or you
didn't realize that you had the ability to annul. Here he knew
all those things, he knew he was empowered to annul and he
did, right, it's just that he got some of the details wrong
that would have allowed him to annul. So it does not seem
from this משנה mishna that that would be a basis for saying
that the idea of ביום שמעו yom sham'o stay start from saying
24 hours. The base of saying what constitutes the same day would
make a difference. No, no, no, the day is the day he
heard because he did know that he had the ability to annul,
that it was a type of a נדר neder he could annul
and so on. Okay, so he presumably the time period does not
change, it goes from the time that he heard. Now, speaking about
hearing there's another interesting question here which I did not have a
full opportunity to explore, which is how did he think it was
his wife when it was his daughter or vice versa? So you
could think like, I don't know, he heard it from behind the
door, they have similar voices, you know, and he just was thought
the other person was talking. But if you look at the ר"ן,
Ran, the ר"ן Ran says נדרה אשתו וסבר שנדרה בתו, nadra ishto
vsavar shenadar bito, the second wide line or the end of the
second wide line: שאמרו לו שבתו נדרה ומתוך כך היפר או קיים.
sha'amru lo shebito nadra umitoch kach hefer o kiyem. He was, it
was reported to him incorrectly. So I'm thinking reported to him, I
thought he had to hear it himself, right? I mean there was
a whole discussion before whether a person can make a שליח shaliach
to annul the vows of his wife and the reason that we
said that a person could not was it required him to be
the one to hear it. He had to hear personally, okay? So
I don't understand the ר"ן Ran and I didn't see others who
said the same thing and I'm sure there's those that ask on
the ר"ן, Ran, but I just did want to point out that
the ר"ן Ran was interesting seeming to be that you could know,
you know, you did not need to directly hear about it. Okay,
so the simpler sense is that I would say that he just
heard from behind a door and he thought it was one was
his wife and it was his daughter or vice versa, yes.
Did you say if he confirmed but by mistake he could annul
it?
Yes, so the other way of reading this משנה mishna the
גמרא gemara will...
It's both directions.
Exactly. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. למאמרא Lema'imra says
the גמרא, Gemara, דיניא אותה דווקא. di'ni otah davka. It says if
he will sort of prevent her, so the אותה otah is דווקא.
davka. He has to know exactly who the woman is whose vow
he is annulling, his wife or his daughter. The אותה otah is
דווקא. davka. Now, not only is there an אותה, otah, but there's
also how you know that he has to know which נדר neder
he is annulling. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
at the ראש Rosh here at the bottom,
he says למאמרא דאותה דווקא Lema'imra di'otah davka דכתיב יניא אותה d'chtiv
yani otah דמשמע שמכיר האישה הנודרת d'mashma shemakir ha-isha ha-noderet because the
אותה otah here is the woman. ומשמע נמי הא דכתיב והפר את
נדרה, v'mashma nami ha-d'chtiv v'heifer et nidrah, he will annul her vow,
right? So her vow, this specific one, שיכיר הנדר, she-yakir ha-neder, he
has to know which vow it is, or what the nature of
the vow is. Interestingly, תוספות Tosafot by the way seems to understand
that the word אותה otah by יניא אותה yani otah refers to
the vow. If you look at תוספות Tosafot למאמרא דאותה דווקא Lema'imra
d'otah davka on the right-hand side, ולכך בעל צריך שידע נדר שנדרה.
u'lekach ba'al tzarich she-yeida neder she-nadra. He understands the word אותה otah
refers not to the woman but to the vow. We've looked at
the פסוקים pesukim before and we've pointed out that the simple sense
is that the אותה, otah, יניא אותה yani otah means prevent her,
the woman, and נדרה nidrah is the vow. תוספות, Tosafot, the ראש
Rosh here has both. Because it says her vow and her, it
means specifically he has to know the woman and the vow that
he is annulling. Now the top of פ"ז עמוד א: Pe-Zayin Amud
Aleph: והא גבי קרעים v'ha gabei kra'im when it comes to doing
a rending of garments for אבילות, aveilus, דכתיב על על, d'chtiv al-al,
it says, well, we'll see, because there the פסוקים pesukim seem to
be very specific in terms of identifying for what purpose or for
whom it is being done, דכתיב על שאול ועל יהונתן בנו, d'chtiv
al Shaul v'al Yehonatan beno, that David rent his garments for Shaul
and for Yehonatan his son, so על על, al-al, meaning very specifically
identifying for whom the rending of the garments was being done.
You would think that if you did it for the wrong person,
it wouldn't count. ותניא, V'tanya, but we teach in a
ברייתא: brayta: אמרו לו מת אביו וקרע, Amru lo meit aviv, v'kara,
they said to a person that your father died and he rent
his garments, ואחר כך נמצא בנו, v'achar kach nimtza b'no, רחמנא ליצלן,
Rachmana litzlan, יצא ידי קריעה, yatza yedei kriya, it counts even though
it was done for the wrong person. So there it says על
al for X, which is certainly at least as specific as יניא
אותה, yani otah, it specifically says it has to be for X,
and we don't require that it be for X. Now, that would
have been a question not just on our משנה, Mishna, that would
be a question on its own terms, like what's the logic about
that, that a קריעה kriya for a wrong person should work besides
the
פסוק? pasuk? That in itself just begs
explanation. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about that. אמרי
לא קשיא, Amri lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בסתם והא במפורש.
Ha b'stam v'ha b'meforesh. It depends whether you're explicitly doing it for
that person and you're wrong, or whether in your mind you're thinking
the wrong person. What labels something to be for X is not
enough of what's going on in your mind. It has to be
because it's been made explicit. Explicit could be like that somebody says
like, "Oh, your daughter did it." I guess going back to my
question about that he has to have heard it himself, he says,
"Oh rat, my daughter made this vow, I'm going to annul my
daughter's vow." That would explicitly label it as an annulling or a
קיום Kiyum or whatever for his daughter. Whereas if it was in
his mind he thought something and he didn't say, then maybe it
will work. And similarly by the rending of the
garments. If somebody says to a person "your father died" and he
does קריעה, kriya, that's labeled as a קריעה kriya for his father.
If he just thought his father died, it would not be. Now,
again, that's not the simple sense of this ברייתא. brayta. The ברייתא
brayta says, אמרו לו מת אביו, amru lo meit aviv, so apparently
it has been labeled. But let's take a look though as the
גמרא Gemara continues. The ר"ן Ran says, look at the ר"ן, Ran,
the ר"ן Ran says we'll have to re-explain this ברייתא, brayta, the
second narrow line in the ר"ן Ran here: הא דתניא אמרו לו
מת אביו וקרע יצא לאו דווקא בשאמרו לו בפירוש מת אביו, Ha
d'tanya amru lo meit aviv v'kara yatza, lav davka b'she'amru lo b'ferush
meit aviv, they didn't explicitly say it, because then that would have
labeled it as a rending for the father, אלא בשאמרו לו מת,
ella b'she'amru lo meit, they said to him, "so-and-so," they said, "oh,
somebody died, I'm so sorry, I heard that somebody died," וסבר אביו,
v'savar aviv, and he assumed it was his father, ונמצא בנו, v'nimtza
b'no, בהא יצא ידי קריעה. b'ha yatza yedei kriya. That would be
okay. So we're saying it doesn't matter what's in your mind,
it can't be explicitly labeled for one person, that way it won't
be able to count for the other
person. Let's get back to the גמרא Gemara and see as the
גמרא Gemara develops this. והתניא, V'hatanya, and we taught in a similarly
in a ברייתא: brayta: אמרו לו מת אביו וקרע, Amru lo meit
aviv v'kara, they said to a person that his father died and
he rent his
garment, ואחר כך נמצא בנו, v'achar kach nimtza b'no, לא יצא ידי
קריעה, lo yatza yedei kriya, he did not fulfill because that was
explicitly... A rending of garments for the father. אמרו לו מת לו
מת, Amru lo met lo met, they just said to him it's
somebody in your family died, we're so sorry to hear that, וכסבר
אביו ve-kasavar aviv and he assumed it was his father, וקרע ve-kara
and he rent his garments, ואחר כך נמצא בנו ve-achar kach nimtza
beno and it turns out it was his son, יצא ידי קריאה,
yatza yedei keriah, then that's okay, his mind does not define the
reality that he had a relative who passed away and he did
קריאה keriah for the, it wasn't like he accidentally was trying,
was accidentally ripped his garment. Apparently it is required at least that
he has intent to do a קריאה keriah for the purpose of
אבילות. aveilus. So that nevertheless, in the context that somebody died, that
satisfies. There's no need to specifically intend the right person. It just
can't be labeled for the wrong person. Okay, so that's what we're
saying by קריאה, keriah, and presumably and therefore the אף af means
it can't be labeled for the wrong person. So presumably we would
say the same by הפרה hafara and קיום, kiyum, that it doesn't
have to have your mind specifically for that right person as long
as it's הפרה hafara in the context of somebody whose vow you
could annul and you did the act of הפרה, hafara, presumably that
satisfies as long as it's not labeled for the wrong person. Now
that seems a little bit strange, right? Yeah, because if anything we
could say קריאה, keriah, I mean they're all both hard, you would
think either one you'd have to have in mind the right person.
But if anything קריאה, keriah, you could say the reality that there's
been some objective demonstration of something shattered and broken in a particular
real world context gives meaning to what that קריאה keriah meant regardless
of what's in the person's head, whereas an act of annulling has
to do with the fact that you do not approve of something,
or an act of קיום kiyum that you do approve of something,
presumably
requires that you know the circumstances,
right? Otherwise it's why should that be a meaningful act? Especially if
you think about the fact that קיום kiyum doesn't even require a
physical activity. קיום kiyum is just as we've seen before בלב, be-lev,
right? הפרה hafara requires to be verbal, if you remember this discussion
before, קיום kiyum does not. So certainly we should care about are
you thinking about the right person or not the right person. Okay,
so it is interesting that based on the analogy, just because yes
we do see that by קריאה keriah sometimes it could work if
it's not explicitly labeled incorrectly, that now we're suggesting that the same
could be by הפרה hafara and קיום, kiyum, which I think would
be strange. Yes.
It's almost lacking or not satisfying in terms of tearing the clothing,
it's just you didn't really resolve it. Yeah. You didn't, I mean
you didn't really resolve that you were tearing the clothing for the
person that you really had loss for.
Right. I mean it doesn't solve that sort of
the internal psychological function. I mean again, it's not clear to me,
while we can very much do focus on the power of these
sort of practices of mourning and how they're so sort of psychologically
beneficial,
it's not like the Rabbis were psychologists and they were saying that
it has to serve that therapeutic
function. They were more interested I think in it as an external
demonstration of a ritual of mourning, but which is not to deny
the power that it has
internally. But I don't think that they saw that as a necessary
part. I mean it's an interesting question. The Rav Soloveitchik talks about
this at great length, what he calls קיום שבלב, kiyum she-be-lev, that
the external expressions of mourning ultimately are fulfilled through only when they're
a manifestation of an internal
experience. So along those lines it's a very good question. Yes.
How do you resolve the contradiction in the ברייתות beraitot that said
the exact opposite, you are יוצא yotze and you aren't יוצא? yotze?
It was through reinterpreting the first ברייתא beraita essentially?
Yes, that's where I went before, the first ברייתא beraita is now
being reinterpreted.
No one would agree to that.
Yeah. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so now that's the answer, that there's a difference between if
it's explicitly mislabeled, and apparently הפרה hafara and הקמה hakama can also
work for the wrong person if it's not explicitly mislabeled. So let's
take a look. But we're not done. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi
amar, כאן בתוך כדי דיבור כאן לאחר כדי דיבור. kan be-toch kedei
dibbur kan le-achar kedei dibbur. So רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying
presumably even if it's explicitly mislabeled, we're going to be even more
lenient, it can work if it's corrected תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei
dibbur. Okay, now normally תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur has to
do with something like a state of mind or it's normally we
think about it as like an opportunity to correct what you just
said, like edit, like ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם בורא פרי
הגפן
שהכל נהיה בדברו. Baruch atah Hashem Elokeinu melech ha-olam borei peri ha-gefen
she-hakol nihiyeh bi-devaro. Okay, so it's like you can sort of still
define your act or still have an opportunity to make corrections over
what you said and so on. But it's less easy to understand
when we're not dealing with an act of speech, right? When we're
dealing with like this physical act of קריאה, keriah, let's take a
look, and you don't even go back and correct it and do
something else that overrides, it's just your frame of mind changes. So
let's take a look. But he said presumably even if it's explicitly
mislabeled, if you are corrected תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, that
would also work. Okay. תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. הא
דקאמר יצא ידי קריאה, ha dekamar yatza yedei kriyah, when does it
work? And now this goes back to the simple read of the
first ברייתא. braita. The simple read of the first ברייתא braita sounds
like even if it was labeled as a tearing for the father,
it works when he discovers that it was for his son. So
there what we said that it works if that שנמצא בנו בתוך
כדי דיבור. shenimtza bno betoch k'dei dibbur. It turns out that it
was the son תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. So then even
if it was explicitly labeled as the father, presumably, it would be
good if the discovery was made within תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei
dibbur. That allows it to be redefined. Okay. הא דאמרת לא יצא
ידי קריאה, ha amart lo yatza yedei kriyah, that which we said
you do not fulfill your obligation, that's לאחר כדי דיבור, le'achar k'dei
dibbur, after כדי דיבור, k'dei dibbur, then it cannot be redefined. Okay.
ותניא v'tanya and we taught similarly in a ברייתא, braita, ותניא v'tanya
sometimes means a question in נדרים nedarim it a lot means as
a statement, and we taught similarly in a ברייתא, braita, מי שיש
לו חולה בתוך ביתו, mi sheyesh lo choleh betoch beito, somebody has
an ill person in his house meaning on his deathbed. ונתעלף v'nitalef
and he fainted ונדמה שמת v'nidmeh shemet and this person thought that
he had died, right, as he stopped looked like he had stopped
breathing or whatever, וקרע v'kara and he rent his garments על המת,
al hamet, and then he actually had died תוך toch so right
afterward. קצת, ktzat, the time a little off. לא יצא ידי קריאה.
lo yatza yedei kriyah. He did not fulfill the obligation. And אמר
רב שמעון בן פזי אמר רב יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא,
amar Rav Shimon ben Pazi amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar
Kappara, לא שנו אלא שמת לאחר כדי דיבור. lo shanu ela shemet
le'achar k'dei dibbur. But then we have the following gloss on this,
that that's only if it's after כדי דיבור. k'dei dibbur. אבל בתוך
כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי. aval betoch k'dei dibbur k'dibbur dami. But if
it's within it, it's like the speech itself and therefore can be
redefined. So now we are saying that a קריאה kriyah just cannot
be mislabeled. It doesn't have to have the right intention. It just
cannot be mislabeled. And even a mislabeling can be corrected, right, תוך
כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. Similarly presumably by הפרה, hafara, although we
didn't say this explicitly, if a person had the wrong person or
whatever thing in mind, that's okay as long as it was only
what was in his mind, it wasn't objectively labeled as such. And
even if it's objectively labeled incorrectly, if a discovery is made תוך
כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, then gets to redefine it. Okay. Now
this is like as I said very interesting because you could still
say I don't get it, right, how could the guy do קריאה
kriyah for somebody who isn't even dead yet, and I'd like the
Monty Python routine, right, I'm not dead yet. Okay. Anyway. So
so oh you're not fooling anybody. Anyway. Okay. So how could somebody
do קריאה kriyah for somebody who isn't even dead yet, and it
counts as an act of קריאה. kriyah. And it seems like right
it's one so like it's one thing to say if it's about
my frame of mind. I was thinking about one thing and then
when I sort of realized differently somehow there's some continuity to my
action, so it's like that later intent can still define what I
was in the middle of the process that somehow I was in
the middle of. By the way though you know it's easier when
it's like an act of speech. When you say בורא פרי הגפן
borei pri hagafen שהכל נהיה בדברו shehakol nihyah bidvaro because then you
could sort of say that you're saying new words, it continues the
act that you're doing and gets to somehow redefine it. Here you're
not continuing the act. I mean if the guy was doing קריאה
kriyah and let's say I don't know he had done the minimum
שיעור shiur of קריאה kriyah and then he was continuing to do
קריאה kriyah and he found out in the second part, maybe there
you could say well you're still part of the process, it can
somehow redefine. But here the guy did קריאה, kriyah, put it down,
and then he has some thought and that somehow redefines, and that's
even more difficult when not only is it that the physical scenario
is there to allow the קריאה kriyah to count, it was just
that it was mislabeled. Then you could say okay, it's mislabeled, תוך
כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, I still somehow am in the immediate
sort of context of it, my thoughts and my realization can somehow
relabel it. Okay. That's like one thing to say something along those
lines. But to say that the guy wasn't even dead and you
went the guy you did a קריאה, kriyah, so I don't understand,
it's not like you're somehow redefining what you did before, you want
something to work for an event that occurred later, you know, you're
sort of like trying to pull that previous act into the future.
So this is really the most difficult statement about תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur or the whole circumstances don't yet exist yet. I
don't know, let's say I shake let's say I sit in a
סוכה sukkah תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur before שקיעה. shkiyah. Anyway.
You know
how do you do something before the circumstances exist yet. Or I'm
מקדש אשה mekadesh isha and she gets her גט get תוך כדי
דיבור toch k'dei dibbur from her other husband, from her first husband,
does that work? Anyway. So so it is very strange. But what
it does sound like is that חז"ל chazal are maybe trying to
define a concept of like simultaneity, you know, that it's sort of
like a principle of אי אפשר לצמצם. i efshar letzamtzem. How precise
can הלכה halacha demand something? We're about to actually and we're giving
you we're in the middle of a of a fellowship on the
שו"ת shut of רב משה Rav Moshe and you know there's an
interesting question right about like
how precise does the square of the תפילין tefillin have to be?
You know what's when is it still considered to be a square?
You know how do you measure the the degree of precision required?
So this might be saying... no that's not enough. So this might
be saying... So this might be saying that the way in which
like if we have a watch that only ticks off in תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur increments, okay? Not in seconds. It only
ticks off in תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur increments. So anything
that occurs תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur is occurring within the
same period of time. So that seems to be what you would
have to say according to this idea that a person did תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur before the other person died, which again
is much more—we wouldn't say it by something else. Like I said,
if I gave a woman a ring of קידושין kiddushin and she
was already married to a guy and he got her גט get
תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, I don't think it would take
effect, right? So it is easier to say that it's a question
about just how do we label the act. Was it labeled for
X or not for X? And somehow it has to do—my frame
of mind can be part of how something is being labeled and
so on, but that is very difficult in this case where the
guy hadn't died yet. So again, what we're saying is תוך כדי—A,
toch k'dei it doesn't have to intentionally be for the right person,
it just can't be mislabeled. And B, even a mislabeling can be
corrected through a—not relabeling, interestingly, but through an awareness that occurs תוך
כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. And then presumably similarly by הפרה hafara
and הקמה, hakama, which is also a big חידוש chiddush because there
you would think much more the right internal state is needed. Certainly
by הקמה hakama that doesn't even require דיבור. dibbur. Nevertheless, presumably by
parallel we are saying that even if the person is thinking about
the wrong woman or about the wrong נדר, neder, as long as
it's not explicitly labeled as such,
you know, he hears a נדר neder and he says, 'I am
מפר mefir it,' right? Then there was a נדר, neder, he said
he was מפר, mefir, he has the power to be מפר, mefir,
right? So even though he thought it was his wife and it
was his daughter and he thought it was this and it was
that, he did the act of הפרה. hafara. A נדר neder was
heard. He has that power and therefore it takes effect. And even
if it was mislabeled, 'Oh rats, my daughter made a נדר, neder,
I'm מפר mefir it,' if he finds out תוך כדי דיבור toch
k'dei dibbur that allows it to be—that awareness allows it to be
relabeled. Yes, Charlie.
Do we have a מחלוקת machlokes already about if I מקדש mekadesh
a woman after she gets divorced or after she—yeah, that was רבי
מאיר.
Rebbe Meir. I was using that as—yes, that was in my mind
because we did דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam yesterday.
But that was to take effect after the divorce. I'm saying let's
say I want it to take effect now and she only gets
her divorce a second later. Yes.
And would that be the same thing with a חכם? chacham? Like
you know, David and I come there for a נדר neder to
the בית דין beis din and you know, they say, 'Alright, fine.
You know, I perform a התרה hatara on and say how regretful
I am תוך כדי toch k'dei of your נדר.' neder. Right. I
mean...
absolutely,
that's a good question because
התרת נדרים hataras nedarim has more to do with uncovering regret and
error as opposed to the more power of the act of הפרה.
hafara. So that might require much more of the specific person. I
mean the more specific concrete awareness rather than just, 'Well, the act
was done in the right context even if you weren't exactly aware.'
That could be. Now I do want to also point out by
the way that the גמרא Gemara doesn't explicitly talk about הקמה. hakama.
I said mentioned before that it's possible to read the משנה mishna
so that הקמה hakama requires—we're also talking about the need of הקמה
hakama to be specific. The גמרא Gemara doesn't explicitly say that. And
as the ראשונים Rishonim point out, the פסוק pasuk that the גמרא
Gemara learned it out from, יניא אותה, yaniyohu osah, is a פסוק
pasuk about הפרה. hafara. So I guess one could in theory say
that all of this is just about הפרה hafara and הקמה hakama
maybe, I don't know, goes by different rules. But again, if anything,
since הקמה hakama is internal, even more would require awareness of the
specific. Okay, but we should point out that the גמרא Gemara does
not explicitly mention הקמה hakama although the ראשונים Rishonim say that that
would follow the same rules, would require specific awareness is also being
referred to in the משנה. mishna. So let's just now read the
גמרא's Gemara conclusion about תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, והלכתא, v'hilchasa, the הלכה halacha is, תוך
כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי, toch k'dei dibbur k'dibbur dami, תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur counts, חוץ ממגדף ועובד עבודת כוכבים ומקדש ומגרש. chutz
mi-megadef v'oved avodas kochavim u-mekadesh u-megaresh.
So there goes my ability to marry a woman before she gets
her גט get from her husband. Okay, so the times that it
does not work is a case of blaspheming and somebody curses God
and then says, 'Oh, I didn't mean it.'
Or, 'I didn't mean God, I meant my mother-in-law' or something. Okay,
so anyway... I'm sorry, I should—okay, apologize to my mother-in-law. Okay, anyway,
or somebody is עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara and then he
says, 'Oh, I didn't mean the בעל, Baal, I meant God,' okay,
when I was bowing down and worshipping or whatever I was doing.
Okay, or he marries a woman and תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei
dibbur he says, 'Whoops, wait, I didn't mean it. I take it
back.' Okay, or he gives a woman a גט get and he
says he didn't mean it. In none of those cases it works.
Now, why not? Okay, so what's the source to say it doesn't
work? By the way, the first thing I should point out that
is a point that all the ראשונים Rishonim say is the logic
we have been saying about תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur is
either the extreme version of a definition of simultaneity or like a
question about your דעת da'as and an act that's in the process,
it still has, you know, ability to sort of be defined because
you're still directing the act and it does have to do with
your frame of mind and you can somehow still in the power
of defining its nature. And that all of those would be דאורייתא
d'oraisa concepts. And it certainly seems from this last thing that we
only exclude... a handful of cases which are real תורה Torah cases
that as a rule this is all דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, right? I mean
for God's sake presumably we're also applying it to the משנה Mishna
which is about הפרה hafara and הקמה hakama which is דאורייתא. d'Oraisa.
So all the ראשונים Rishonim ask that this is a contradiction to
רבינו תם Rabeinu Tam's theory because רבינו תם Rabeinu Tam's theory is
that תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibur was a rabbinic תקנה takkanah
to help grease the wheels of commerce that allowed people the ability
to back out of a deal within the first few seconds and
that was seen as somehow something
necessary to make it more tolerable to do business.
Now you could say that makes business harder because you can back
out rather... anyway, but רבינו תם Rabeinu Tam made it into a
rabbinic תקנה. takkanah. Here it sounds very, very much that it's דאורייתא
d'Oraisa and it's a point that all the ראשונים Rishonim point out.
Now what's the reason that these things about מגדף, megadef, עובד עבודה
זרה, oved avodah zarah, קידושין kiddushin and גירושין geirushin are different? No
פסוק pasuk is being quoted, I mean no פסוק pasuk was quoted
for תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibur, but no פסוק pasuk is
being quoted here or no other basis. So the ראשונים Rishonim basically
say it's just basically מסברא misvara because these things are so weighty
that you cannot say that
you did not
fully think it through and that you're
reconsidering. Clearly your act was intended and what you're thinking now is
like a different thought but it cannot redefine your frame of mind.
You would not have undergone something as weighty and as serious unless
your first frame of mind was very clear. Okay so take a
look at the ר"ן Ran for example. The
ר"ן Ran
says it's one, two, three, four, five lines down in the wide
lines. He says like this: ולא ידענא מיהו מאי שנא הני ואינהו
לרבנן הכי. v'lo yadana mihu mai shna hani v'inhu l'Rabanan hachi.
I don't know why these are different. ונראה בעיני דבשאר מילי דלאו
חמירי כולי האי. v'nireh b'einai d'bishar milei d'lav chamiri kulei hai. Normal
types of things we engage in in the world that are not
as weighty. כשאדם עושה אותם לא בגמר דעתו הוא עושה. k'she'adam oseh
osam lo b'gmar da'ato hu oseh.
Whenever you do something you're never like you'll do things even if
in your mind you haven't 100% made up your mind about it.
אלא דעתו שיוכל לחזור בו תוך כדי דיבור. ella da'ato sheyuchal lachzor
bo toch k'dei dibur. You always also are sort of holding on
to a little tentativeness in terms of it and wait, wait, I'm
still thinking it through. So you want to sort of still hold
there's a little reservation in your דעת, da'as, which doesn't explain the
קריעה kriyah issue, rending garment on a mate, but okay. Things that
are דעת da'as related certainly. הני כיון דחמירי כולי האי אין אדם
עושה אותם אלא בהסכמה גמורה. hani keivan d'chamiri kulei hai ein adam
oseh osam ella b'haskama gmura.
A person would never do them until he had completely unreserved intention.
ומשום הכי חזרה אפילו תוך כדי דיבור לא מהני. umishum hachi chazara
afilu toch k'dei dibur lo mahani. And therefore any direct attempt to
retract is no good because your דעת da'as at the time is
considered to have been unreserved and complete. Okay and then he goes
on and quotes the sort of position of רבינו תם Rabeinu Tam
which he rejects. So one way is to say that your דעת
da'as in these times is considered complete. The other possibility is to
say the action itself is so weighty that it's not sort of
the action speaks louder than words as it were. So when the
action itself is so weighty you don't have the power to say
I'm going to redefine it. Meaning even if we said that your
frame of mind was the same, a person that marries a woman
has the same, he's not 100% sure but he's still going through
with it as he does when he's buying a car. Who knows?
Okay, you see I'm getting all ready for מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin
where we commodify the woman. Anyway, but people always have these reservations.
But because it is something that is so weighty either affects the
status of another person or does with a person's sort of relationship
with God or whatever,
then הלכה halacha defines that the act cannot be redefined. An act
of that weight is final and cannot be redefined. So one way
or the other those are the limits to תוך כדי דיבור. toch
k'dei dibur. So a very fascinating סוגיא sugya in the גמרא, Gemara,
not fully explored here but very important about this issue about קריעה
kriyah after the before the fact that the guy had died, the
most extreme example, and this difference between as I said whether intent
itself matters or it's a question about how the act was labeled.
Right now we go on to the next משנה. Mishna. Yes?
There was a case the Queens חברה קדישא Chevra Kadisha had where
there were two women in a nursing home with similar names, one
died and they contacted the wrong sister. And they ended up doing
all the rituals and then the living relative called the שבעה shiva
house.
Oh my God.
Why are you calling me in the last couple...
oh my God, oh my God, look at that.
There you go, thank you for that. Okay wow, pretty tragic. Next
משנה: Mishna: אמרה. Amra. A woman said, קונם תאנים וענבים שאלו שאני
טועמת. Konam t'einim va'anavim she'elu she'ani to'emet.
These figs and grapes are forbidden to me that I should not
taste them, or that regarding my tasting of them. קיים לתאנים כולו
קיים. Kiyam l'te'einim kulo kiyam.
So this is my question I asked before, exactly a case almost
exactly like this. The husband basically said I am מקים mekim the
idea about the figs. Great, I hate figs also. Okay, I establish
your נדר neder about the figs. So now that because I was
מקיים mekayem part of the נדר, neder, it's מקיים mekayem the whole
נדר neder and I cannot annul the grapes even if I wanted
to. הפר לתאנים, Heifer l'te'enim, if
however I annulled the figs, okay, אינו מופר עד שיפר אף לענבים.
eino mufar ad sheyafer af l'anavim.
It's ineffective until I annul also the grapes. The פשט pshat of
this משנה mishnah is that it either works on the whole נדר,
neder, either everything or nothing.
הקמה, hakama, affirming it, is even on a part, affirms the whole
thing. An annulling about by a part is not an annulling. To
annul you have to annul the whole thing. Okay, which in a
certain sense makes sense. The נדר neder already exists, my wife already
made it, it's a real thing. To wipe it away requires, you
know, more strength than to just reaffirm what's already there. So even
a little reaffirming establishes it, roots it. Okay, whereas if I want
to annul it, I gotta reject the whole נדר. neder. Alright, that's
a simple sense. I should point out that the ר״ן Ran suggests
a different read, which I don't think is פשט pshat at all,
which is that it says if I am מיפר meifer for the
figs, it's not מופר mufar for the grapes until I am מיפר
meifer for the grapes. But for the figs, it does work. That
הפרה hafarah can work on part. So קיום kiyum on part is
a קיום kiyum on the whole. הפרה hafarah on part, the simple
sense of the משנה mishnah is a הפרה hafarah on nothing. But
the ר״ן Ran reads says it's אינו מופר eino mufar for the
grapes עד שיפר אף לענבים. ad sheyafer af l'anavim. I know it's
not פשט. pshat. But the ר״ן Ran suggests a read of the
משנה mishnah that הפרה hafarah on part does work for that part.
It's not פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat is all or nothing. To
affirm what's already there, a little קיום kiyum works for the whole
thing. A little הפרה hafarah does not work, you need to do
a whole הפרה. hafarah.
Okay,
an ounce of קיום kiyum is better...
a little קיום kiyum goes a long way.
An ounce of קיום kiyum is better than a pound...
Exactly. אמר קונם תאנה שאני טועמת וענבה שאני טועמת. Amar konam te'enah
she'ani to'emet v'anavah she'ani to'emet. Let's say she uses the word שאני
טועמת she'ani to'emet to separate out the two parts of her vow.
I won't eat a קונם konam on this grape that I won't
eat regarding my eating of it and on this olive regarding my
eating... not olive, whatever, fig. Okay, so she didn't say... I said
grape first. Fig and grape. So she didn't say the word קונם.
konam. If she said the word קונם konam for each one, clearly
they're separate vows. She didn't say the word קונם konam for each
one separately, but she did say שאני טועמת she'ani to'emet separately. Okay,
she used these sort of verb separately. הרי אלו שני נדרים, harei
elu shenei nedarim, that's the... suffices to make it two vows and
with the relevance that you do a קיום kiyum on one, it's
not a קיום kiyum on the other. You do a הפרה hafarah
on one, it works. Okay, 'cause now it doesn't really matter, do
you call something one vow or two vows.
Yeah, but let's say my... in my hybrid case, like, you know,
he's sort of trying to do both at the same time. I
like it for לתאנים l'te'enim but I don't like it for ענבים.
anavim.
So then what? The idea is there's no way you could do
that according to the simple read of this משנה. mishnah. You either
have to get rid of the whole thing or
מקיים mekayem the whole thing.
What have I done? What have I done? According to the ר״ן,
Ran, what you could do is
you could do a הפרה hafarah first on the part you don't
like and probably have to let the clock run out on the
other half and then it'll be a קיום. kiyum. I wonder if
you could first do a הפרה hafarah and then a קיום kiyum
once one half is removed, could the קיום kiyum on the other
half work without affecting the first half?
According to the
simple read of
the משנה, mishnah, then I've done nothing?
Exactly. There's no way.
I have not been מיפר. meifer.
Exactly. Well, if you did, if you tried to do a partial
הפרה, hafarah, you've done nothing. Correct.
Or a partial הקמה? hakama?
No, then you've done הקמה hakama of the whole thing.
No, I mean, I've got not, meaning partial הפרה, hafarah, like I
only did this part and then I really said I don't like
the other part.
Doesn't matter. As soon as you did a הקמה, hakama, that works
for the whole thing.
Really? If he said I'm מקיים mekayem it for the תאנה te'enah
but not for the ענבה, anavah, so it's too late?
You mean like if you did a... if you did a הפרה
תוך כדי דיבור hafara toch kedei dibbur of the הקמה, hakama, would
it say that the הקמה, hakama, would it neutralize the הקמה? hakama?
Yeah, I don't know, it's a good question. Okay, let's see the
גמרא. Gemara. מני מתניתין? Mani matnitin? Who's our משנה? mishnah? רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. היא רבי ישמעאל. Hi Rabbi Yishmael. דתניא, Ditanya, taught in
a ברייתא, braita, אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו, Ishah yekimenu v'ishah yeferenu, her
husband will establish and her husband will annul it.
אמרה קונם תאנים וענבים אלו שאני טועמת. Amrah konam te'enim va'anavim elu
she'ani to'emet. I... these figs and dates that regarding my eating of
it. קיים לתאנים כולו קיים. Kayam l'te'enim kulo kayam. If he was
establish it for the figs, it works for the whole thing. A
partial קיום kiyum works for the whole thing. הפר לתאנים, Heifer l'te'enim,
if he annulled it for the figs, so אינו מופר עד שיפר
אף לענבים. eino mufar ad sheyafer af l'anavim. Then it has to
work, then it's nothing until he does the grapes as well. Of
course the פשט pshat is it's absolutely nothing. A partial הפרה hafarah
is nothing. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael. Those are the word
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So our משנה mishnah clearly is רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. That's exactly our משנה. mishnah. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi
Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, הרי הוא אומר, Harei hu
omer, the verse says, אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו. Ishah yekimenu v'ishah yeferenu.
Her husband will establish, her husband will annul. So it links the
two. So they have to operate with the same, you know,
efficaciousness. So מה יקימנו ממנו? Mah yekimenu mimenu? And how do we
know that a partial הקמה hakama works, right? I just gave you
a סברא sevara for saying it. But what's the verse that says
it? So it's a play on words. יקימנו. Yekimenu. So the מ
mem in the word יקימנו yekimenu means יקים, yakim, right, is from
the word יקים. yakim. But we're using the מ mem in a
דרשה drasha to say יקים ממנו. yakim mimenu. So as long as
you do a הקמה hakama even on only part of it, a
piece of it. part of it, that works as a הקמה hakama
for the whole thing. That's where we get the idea that a
partial הקמה hakama works. Well once we've established that for a הקמה,
hakama, so אף יסירנו ממנו. af yesirenu mimenu. So even for the
הפרה, hafara, a partial הפרה hafara works. So Rabbi Akiva agrees that
it's all or nothing, but he just says we'll take our lead
from the הקמה. hakama. Since a partial הקמה hakama is a full
הקמה, hakama, a partial הפרה hafara is a full הפרה. hafara. That's
Rabbi Akiva. Now there's another possibility. Rabbi Yishmael would say back, מכתיב
יפר ממנו? mi-ktiv yafer mimenu?
It doesn't. It says יקימנו. yakimenu. You have the word by יקימנו,
yakimenu, the ממנו mimenu idea. You don't have that word by יסירנו.
yesirenu. For Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva would respond, מקיש הפרה להקמה. makish
hafara le-hakama. No, but it links. מה הקמה ממנו אף הפרה ממנו.
ma hakama mimenu af hafara mimenu. Okay.
So far that just spells out what we already read. That yes
it's true the דרשה drasha is by הקמה, hakama, but they're linked.
So according to this read, it's all or nothing. We agree that
הקמה hakama partial is all, and then there's the debate. Rabbi Yishmael
says הפרה hafara partial is nothing, and Rabbi Akiva says הפרה hafara
works like הקמה. hakama. Partial הפרה hafara is like a full הפרה.
hafara. אמר רבי עקיבא. Amar Rabbi Akiva. Now we're going to introduce
a third opinion. Because if you think about it, right, even assuming
it's all or nothing, what would be the three possibilities? Actually, logically
there would be four, but okay. Anyway, right, the four what are
the four possibilities? Partial is everything for both. Partial is nothing for
both. Partial works for הקמה hakama and doesn't work for הפרה. hafara.
Or the reverse. Now the third the fourth possibility is not at
all possible because we've right, because there's no basis for saying a
partial הפרה hafara works completely.
But logically הקמה hakama works what you're מקיימנו mekayem it for or
what you're מיפר. meifer.
Right. But assuming we're all buying into the idea all or nothing,
right, if it's all or nothing there are four possibilities, right? Everybody
got there are four possibilities? Right, partial הקמה hakama partial הפרה hafara
is a full הקמה hakama full הפרה. hafara. Partial הקמה hakama partial
הפרה hafara is nothing. Or partial הקמה hakama works is a full
one, partial הפרה hafara is nothing. Okay, so we now have done
two of the and so so there are really three of the
logical four, we've done two and now we're going to introduce the
third. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו דברי רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא. zu
divrei Rabbi Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva. That's the position of Rabbi Yishmael and
Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Yishmael says partial הקמה hakama is everything, partial הפרה
hafara is zero. Rabbi Akiva says they're both everything. אבל חכמים אומרים,
Aval chachamim omrim, but the sages say, מקיש הקמה להפרה. makish hakama
le-hafara. It works in the opposite direction. מה הפרה מה שהפר הפר,
ma hafara ma she-heifer heifer, אף הקמה מה שקיים קיים. af hakama
ma she-kiyam kiyam. Now the same way הפרה hafara works partially, הקמה
hakama works partially. Now really, what you would have liked to have
said, which is the same way הפרה hafara partial is zero, הקמה
hakama partial is zero. Right? This sounds like yes, given the four
possibilities, am I have I lost everybody now?
He says it's avocados and grapes, and you מיפר meifer for avocados
and מקיימנו mekayem for grapes, that works. That sounds like exactly what
I understand.
I'm just saying that's yes. But the way we laid it out,
it sounded like everybody agreed that it was all or nothing. So
if it's all or nothing, right, you have the possibility הקמה hakama
and הפרה. hafara. Okay. If it's all or nothing, so what are
the four possibilities? So one possibility is all all. One possibility is
nothing nothing. Right? One possibility is all and nothing. And I guess
in theory the other possibility is all and nothing, but there's no
reason to say that הפרה hafara is better than הקמה hakama in
that regard. We're all assuming so if you assume all or nothing
and you start by assuming that הקמה hakama is more powerful, so
these are your possibilities, right? So this is the possibility of Rabbi
Yishmael.
Okay. This is the possibility of Rabbi Akiva. And this could have
been a third possibility, right? The same way a partial הפרה hafara
is nothing a partial הקמה hakama is nothing. Okay. But the last
line in the גמרא Gemara seems to question the all or nothing
approach, right, seems to introduce a new idea that actually partial is
possible. So comes in the last line of the גמרא Gemara and
says uh-uh, who said it's all or nothing? Partial is possible too.
So this is partial and this is partial. Okay. And that's how
that's the third opinion that rejects the all or nothing type of
an approach. Okay.
I did in my case then I understand.
Right. Okay. All right. So let's take a look.
One minute.
So if you take a look, the ר"ן Ran however to keep
the nice structure that we had, had a different גרסה. girsa. If
you took a look four lines before the lines get wide in
the ר"ן, Ran, he says the following. לפיכך נראה גרסת קצת ספרים
עיקר, Lefichach nireh girsaat ktsat sefarim ikar, וגרסי הכי. ve-garsai hachi.
Here's a different גרסה girsa of that last punchline of the גמרא.
Gemara. וגרסי הכי. ve-garsai hachi.
Three lines before the lines... lines get wide, mid-size, before the mid-size
lines. קצת ספרים עיקר דגרסי הכי: Katzas s'farim ikar, d'garsi hachi: אבל
חכמים אומרים מה הפרה מה שהפיר לא הופר אף הקמה מה שקיים
לא קיים. Aval chachamim omrim, mah hafarah mah shehefir lo hufar af
hakama mah shekiyam lo kiyam. וכן גרסת רבנו משה בר נחמן ז"ל
בהלכותיו. V'chen girsas Rabbeinu Moshe bar Nachman zal b'hilchosav.
Okay?
So according to the ר"ן's Ran גירסא girsa the last opinion is
exactly zero zero. The same way הפרה hafarah partial הפרה hafarah does
nothing, הקמה hakama partial הקמה hakama does nothing.
It doesn't say nothing. It has no effect.
To a rest, okay. So basically, one way of reading this is
everybody agrees that it's an all-or-nothing deal. Okay? And therefore, and everybody
agrees that at least conceptually, partial הקמה hakama should be stronger. So
there are three logic possibilities and those three logical possibilities are spread
out. Rabbi Ishmael says partial הקמה hakama is everything, partial הפרה hafarah
is nothing. Rabbi Akiva says partial is everything for both. And whoever
the חכמים chachamim are saying that according to this other גירסא girsa
that partial is nothing for both. Okay, so that's the three logical
possibilities if you take an all-or-nothing approach. The other read of the
last line of the משנה Mishna of the גמרא Gemara rejects the
all-or-nothing approach and says you can have a partial הקמה hakama and
you can have a partial הפרה. hafarah. Right. That would be the
חכמים. chachamim. Well, depends what your גירסא girsa is. The ר"ן Ran
פוסק paskens like the חכמים chachamim but he says it's nothing for
both. Okay, let me take, tell you what the רמב"ם Rambam says,
what do we say? נדרים י"ג. Nedarim Yud Gimmel.
I'll tell you what the רמב"ם Rambam says.
He probably has our גירסא. girsa. I don't know why I'm saying
that. Because that would make it fun. עשה תאנים וענבים כאחד ואמר
הרי הם עלי בשבועה, בין שעשה עצמה בכל המינין, וקיים לתאנים והפר
לענבים, או שקיים לענבים והפר לתאנים, מה שקיים קיים ומה שהופר מופר,
וכן כל כיוצא בזה. Asah te'einim va'anavim k'echad v'amar harei hem alai
bishvuah, bein she'asah atzmah b'chol haminin, v'kiyam late'einim v'hefir la'anavim, o shekiyam
la'anavim v'hefir late'einim, mah shekiyam kiyam u'mah shehufar mufar, v'chen kol kayotzei
bazeh. So he has our גירסא. girsa. Partial works for both. Okay.
Yeah, like the חכמים. chachamim. Okay. אמר קונם תאנים Amar konam te'einim
and now we have the idea that it's separate things if she
says the word שאני טועמת שאני טועמת, she'ani to'emes she'ani to'emes, that
breaks it up into two נדרים. nedarim.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא מתניתין רבי שמעון היא דאמר
עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. Amar Rava: Masnisin Rabbi Shimon hi,
d'amar ad sheyomar shvuah l'chol echad v'echad. You might remember this that
if I take an oath that you say that I owe you
money and I deny it with an oath, I have to bring
a קרבן korban and be מוסיף חומש mosif chomesh etc. So what's
to define how many oaths I made? You all five of you
come to me and I borrowed a hundred dollars from each of
you, okay, because I'm regularly hitting up my friends. And then each
of you come and say 'Where's the money you owe me?' and
I say 'שבועה Shvuah I don't owe any of you any money.'
So that's one oath and I take one קרבן, korban, bring one
קרבן korban if I'm lying. Let's say I says 'שבועה Shvuah I
don't owe you and שבועה Shvuah I don't owe you and שבועה
Shvuah I don't owe you,' that's five קרבנות. korbanos. Let's say I
say 'שבועה Shvuah I don't owe you or you or you or
you or you.' One or five? So that's the debate. So the
חכמים chachamim say it's not a separate
קרבן korban עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד, ad sheyomar shvuah l'chol
echad v'echad, שבועה shvuah I don't owe you. So now that's our
משנה Mishna because for our משנה Mishna if you say קונם konam
that I won't eat תאנים te'einim or ענבים, anavim, it's still considered
one נדר neder unless you break it up more. But I should
say it's not exactly parallel. If you wanted to make it parallel
you would have to say קונם לכל אחד ואחד. konam l'chol echad
v'echad. קונם konam I won't eat תאנים te'einim and קונם konam I
won't eat ענבים anavim and קונם konam I won't eat this. Right?
Is the fact that you said קונם ענבים שאני טועמת ותאנים שאני
טועמת konam anavim she'ani to'emes v'te'einim she'ani to'emes is not as much
of a break up as reusing that sort of key technical word
קונם konam like the key technical word שבועה. shvuah. But nevertheless, רבא's
Rava saying it's close enough to the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that you would require something more significant to break things up
into separate, into separate נדרים. nedarim.
What about Rabbi Yossi?
Well, within the discussion of what
constitutes, what do you call it?
דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino l'veinah, or עינוי נפש, inoui nefesh, I
don't think we're saying that he's the only תנא tanna speaking here.
Okay, or if you want you could say he's following this opinion.
All right, let's start, let's read the next משנה. mishna. There we
are, we're two דף daf ahead. I don't know what we're going
to do with all our reserve. יודע אני שיש נדרים. Yodeia ani
sheyesh nedarim. Okay, this is the issue that we discussed, right, about
when does the clock start ticking? יודע אני שיש נדרים. Yodeia ani
sheyesh nedarim. You know what, let's just stop here. We're far, far
enough ahead and it's going to get a little complicated here moving
forward. Okay, so we'll pick up here tomorrow.